Conway Zirkle Collection 1948-1966 Mss.B.Z67
American Philosophical Society
Conway Zirkle Collection
1948-1966
Mss.B.Z67
American Philosophical Society
1.5 Linear feet
A botanist and historian of science at the University of Pennsylvania, Conway Zirkle published on the history of evolutionary thought and genetics, with a particular interest in the discipline as practiced in the Soviet Union. The Zirkle Papers consist of approximately one linear foot of materials accrued by Zirkle during research for his book on Lysenko-era biology in the Soviet Union, The Death of Science in Russia (1949). Among the miscellaneous materials in the collection are four volumes (0.5 linear feet) of pressed specimens of ferns and algae.
1.5 linear feet
Zirkle, Conway, 1895-1972
Box 1-3
Biographical/Historical note
A botanist and historian of science at the University of Pennsylvania, Conway Zirkle published on the history of evolutionary thought, with a particular interest in the discipline as practiced in the Soviet Union. His major works included The Death of Science in Russia (Philadelphia, 1949) and Evolution, Marxian Biology, and the Social Scene (Philadelphia, 1959).
Scope and Contents note
Consisting largely of newspaper clippings and translations from Pravda, the Zirkle Collection was assembled by Conway Zirkle while preparing his book on Soviet biology during the Lysenko era, Death of Science in Russia. It focuses primarily on the Soviet rejection of the chromosomal theory of inheritance and Mendel-Morgan genetics in favor of the biology of Michurin and Lysenko, and the social and political context. In addition to a small volume of correspondence, the collection includes typescript essays on Lysenko by L.C. Dunn, H.J. Muller, Theodosius Dobzhansky, and N.I. Vavilov.
Among the even smaller number of miscellaneous items in the collection is an important 10 page letter from James McKeen Cattell addressed to Allyn A. Young of the Committee on Academic Freedom regarding Cattell's dismissal from Columbia in 1917. There are, in addition, a group of 22 letters of congratulations to Zirkle upon his retirement from the University of Pennsylvania, a copy of Henry H. Dale's resignation from the USSR Academy of Sciences in 1948, materials used by Zirkle in research for his article "Animals impregnated by the wind," and four volumes containing specimens of pressed ferns and algae.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Zirkle Papers were presented to the APS by the Bryn Mawr College Library, 1972.
Bibliography
Zirkle, Conway, Death of Science in Russia: the Fate of Genetics as Described in Pravda and elsewhere (Philadelphia: Univ. of Pennsylvania, 1949).
Call no.: 575.12 Z6d.
Zirkle, Conway, Evolution, Marxian Biology, and the Social Scene (Philadelphia: Univ. of Pennsylvania, 1949).
Call no.: 575 Z6
Related Archival Materials note
Additional material on Soviet biology and Lysenko is located in the papers of L. C. Dunn (B D917), Theodosius Dobzhansky (B D65), Michael Lerner (B L563), and Curt Stern (Ms. Coll. 5), among others.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Academic Freedom of Science in Russia Manuscripts (13 pages) Circa 1957
An Appraisal of Science in the U.S.S.R. Manuscripts (23 pages) 1951
Biology in the U.S.S.R. Manuscripts (4 pages) 1949
Cattell, James McKeen Correspondence (9 pages) 1917
Communist Pseudo-Science in Agriculture Manuscripts (10 pages) 1955
Concerning the Inheritance of Acquired Characteristics Manuscripts (21 pages) n.d.
Dale, Henry Hallett, Sir Correspondence (3 pages) 1948
Death of a Science in Russia Manuscripts (7 folders) 1948-1959
Destruction of Science in Russia Manuscripts (4 pages) n.d.
Deutsch, Albert -- Degradation of Soviet Science Manuscripts (3 pages) 1948
Dimitrova, Elena -- Lysenko in Bulgaria Manuscripts (3 pages) 1949
Divergent attitudes toward science in east-west tension Manuscripts (7 pages) n.d.
Dobzhansky, Theodosius -- End of Genetics in the Soviet Union Manuscripts (2 folders) 1948-1949
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Concerning the Lysenko Report Manuscripts (4 pages) 1948
Evolution, Marxian Biology and the Social Scene Manuscripts (16 pages) 1959
Fall of a Charlatan Manuscripts (4 pages) 1956
Genetics in Russia Manuscripts (8 pages) 1956
Genetics, the science of heredity Manuscripts (3 pages) n.d.
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict -- Presidential address to Phi Sigma Manuscripts (5 pages) n.d.
Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich Manuscripts (3 folders) 1952-1958, n.d.
Moore, Barrington -- Terror and Progress, U.S.S.R. Manuscripts (7 pages) 1954
Muller, Hermann Joseph -- Destruction of a science in the U.S.S.R. Manuscripts (2 folders) 1948-1949
Muller, Hermann Joseph -- Genetics in relation to modern science Manuscripts (9 pages) Circa 1948
Muller, Hermann Joseph -- Rise and fall of genetics in the U.S.S.R. Manuscripts (6 pages) n.d.
Pravda Records (5 folders) 1948, n.d.
Prezent, Isaac Israilevich -- Creative Darwinism in the Soviet Union Manuscripts (31 pages) 1947
Science and the Scientist in the Soviet Union Manuscripts (20 pages) Circa 1956
Science in Russia Manuscripts (3 pages) n.d.
Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich -- Botanical-geographic principles of selection Manuscripts (84 pages) 1935
Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944; Dale, Henry H. (Henry Hallett), 1875-; Davitashvili, L.; Demidov, Sergei Federovich; Deutsch, Albert, 1905-1961; Dimitrova, Elena; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974; Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict, 1878-1958; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich, 1898-1976; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Nachtsheim, Hans, 1890-1979; Shmalgauzen, I. I. (Ivan Ivanovich), 1884-1963; Vavilov, N. I. (Nikolai Ivanovich), 1887-1943; Agriculture--Soviet Union; Algae.; Evolution (Biology)--Soviet Union; Ferns; Genetics--Soviet Union
- Correspondence and manuscripts, 1948-1966; 2 boxes
  - Academic Freedom of Science in Russia, Circa 1957; 13.0 p. (Box 1)
    Academic freedom; History of biology, especially genetics -- U.S.S.R.; Lectures, public speaking; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Animals Impregnated by the wind. [see also: Impregnation by the wind] (Box 1)
  - An Appraisal of Science in the USSR, 1951; 23.0 p. (Box 1)
    Academic freedom; American Association for the Advancement of Science; Conferences and symposia; Genetics -- U.S.S.R.; Greben, Leonid Kondratevich; Lectures, public speaking; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Political issues; Publication -- Pravda; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Biological Abstracts (Box 1)
  - Biology in the USSR, 1949; 4.0 p. (Box 1)
    Conferences and symposia; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Birthday Greetings, 1966 (Box 1)
  - British literature in the Eighteenth Century (Box 1)
  - Cattell, J. McKeen (James McKeen), 1917; 9.0 p. (Box 1)
    Academic freedom; Biographical and personal data; Columbia University; Committee activities; Political issues; World War I -- Impact on science
  - Checkmenev, E. M. (Box 1)
  - Communist Pseudo-Science in Agriculture, 1955; 10.0 p. (Box 1)
    Botany and plant genetics; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Lectures, public speaking; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Mendel, Gregor; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Conant, George H. (Box 1)
  - Concerning a hemophiliac family (Box 1)
  - Concerning the inheritance of acquired characteristics, n.d.; 21.0 p. (Box 1)
    Kammerer, Paul; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Dale, Henry Hallett, Sir, 1948; 3.0 p. (Box 1)
    Academy of Sciences -- U.S.S.R.; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - An Institute's Serious Mistakes, Davitashvili, L. (Box 1)
  - Death of a Science in Russia, 1948-1959; 7 folders (Box 1)
    Academy of Sciences -- U.S.S.R.; Botany and plant genetics; Genetics of plants; History of biology, especially genetics; Kammerer, Paul; Lectures, public speaking; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Publication -- Death of a Science in Russia; Publication -- Pravda; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
    - Death of a Science in Russia (Box 1)
    - Death of a Science in Russia [Preface to the Japanese Edition] (Box 1)
    - Death of a Science in Russia [Manuscripts - not used], 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Degeneration of plants (Box 1)
  - Demidov, S. F. (Box 1)
  - Destruction of Science in Russia, n.d.; 4.0 p. (Box 1)
    History of biology, especially genetics; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Degradation of Soviet Science, 1948; 3.0 p.; Deutsch, Albert, 1905-1961 (Box 1)
    Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Sonneborn, Tracy M.; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Lysenko in Bulgaria, 1949; 3.0 p.; Dimitrova, Elena (Box 1)
    Conferences and symposia -- Bulgaria; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Mendel, Gregor; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Morgan, Thomas Hunt; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Divergent attitudes toward science in east-west tension, n.d.; 7.0 p. (Box 1)
    Academic freedom; Philosophy of science; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975 (Box 1)
  - End of genetics in the Soviet Union, 1948-1949; 9.0 p.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975 (Box 1)
    Academic freedom; Anthropology; International Congress of Genetics; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Political issues; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Concerning the Lysenko report, 1948; 4.0 p.; Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974 (Box 1)
    Mendel, Gregor; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich
  - Early ideas of inbreeding crossbreeding and hybrid-vigor (Box 1)
  - Evolution, Marxian Biology, and the Social Scene, 1959; 16.0 p. (Box 1)
    Darwin, Charles; Evolution; History of biology, especially genetics; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Political issues -- Marx, Karl; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Evolution: Miscellaneous notes (Box 1)
  - Fall of a charlatan, 1956; 4.0 p. (Box 1)
    Genetics of plants; Lectures, public speaking; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - I write as I please... the Lysenko theory and the Saturday Review, Fast, Howard (Box 1)
  - Genetics in Russia, 1956; 8.0 p. (Box 1)
    Genetics -- U.S.S.R.; History of biology, especially genetics -- U.S.S.R.; Kammerer, Paul; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Genetics: the science of heredity, n.d.; 3.0 p. (Box 1)
    Genetics; Lectures, public speaking; University of Pennsylvania; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Glushchenko, I (Box 1)
  - Presidential address to Phi Sigma Societies, n.d.; 5.0 p.; Goldschmidt, Richard (Box 1)
    Genetics -- Amphibians; Kammerer, Paul; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Lectures, public speaking; Political issues; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Havas, László (Box 1)
  - Herbert, Danby (Box 1)
  - Herbert, Henry L. (Box 1)
  - How to find a book in a Library (Box 1)
  - Column In Daily Worker, Howard, Milton (Box 1)
  - Impregnation by the wind - Miscellany. (Box 1)
  - Items in the history of biology (Box 1)
  - Kaftanov, S. (Box 2)
  - The knowledge of generation in the Renaissance (Box 2)
  - Life of science. Introduction (Box 2)
  - Lysenko, Trofim Denishovich, 1952-1958; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Darwin, Charles; Evolution; Genetics of plants; Human genetics; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Malthus, Thomas Robert; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Political issues; Population, demography; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - Lysenko, Trofim Denishovich (Box 2)
    - Lysenko miscellaneous notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Marxism and the arts (Box 2)
  - Mitin, M. B. (Box 2)
  - "Terror and Progress, USSR", 1954; 7.0 p.; Moore, Barrington, Jr. (Box 2)
    Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Mossige, Jeanne Coyne (Box 2)
  - Destruction of a science in the USSR (Manuscript), 1948-1949; Muller, H. J. (Box 2)
    Academic freedom; Agol, I. J.; Ethical issues; Genetics -- U.S.S.R.; International Congress of Genetics -- Seventh Congress; Levit, Solomon G.; Political issues; Prezent, Isaac Israilevich; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Destruction of a science in the USSR (Published), 1948-1949; Muller, H. J. (Box 2)
    Academic freedom; Agol, I. J.; Ethical issues; Genetics -- U.S.S.R.; International Congress of Genetics -- Seventh Congress; Levit, Solomon G.; Political issues; Prezent, Isaac Israilevich; Publication; Russian politics and science; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Genetics in relation to modern science, Circa 1948; 9.0 p.; Muller, H. J. (Box 2)
    Academic freedom; Evolution; Genetics; International Congress of Genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Rise and fall of genetics in the USSR, 6.0 p.; Muller, H. J. (Box 2)
    Agol, I. J.; Genetics; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; International Congress of Genetics -- Seventh Congress; Levit, Solomon G.; Political issues; Russian politics and science -- Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Das Ende der sowjetischen Pseudogenetik, Nachtsheim, Hans, 1890-1979 (Box 2)
  - Nemchinov, V. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - Pravda, 1948, n.d.; 5 folders (Box 2)
    Dubinin, Nikolai Petrovich; Genetics of plants; Lenin All-Union Academy of Agricultural Sciences; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Publication -- Pravda; Russian politics and science
    - Pravda: At the Session of the V.I. Lenin All-Union Academy of Agricultural Sciences (Box 2)
    - Pravda: Higher the Banners of Advanced, Michurinist Biological Science (Box 2)
    - Pravda: [Lysenko] various dates, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Pravda: [Lysenko] Editorial (Box 2)
    - Pravda: Reply to Muller; 1948 December 14 (Box 2)
  - Creative Darwinism in the Soviet Union, 1947; 31.0 p.; Prezent, I. I. (Box 2)
    Darwin, Charles; Evolution; Genetics of plants; History of biology, especially genetics; Human genetics; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Printed items on Lysenko (Box 2)
  - Refutation of Joravsky's review of his book (Box 2)
  - Rehabilitating a Soviet scientist (Box 2)
  - Return of quackery to Russian medicine (Box 2)
  - Review of Alexander G. Korol: Soviet Education for Science and Technology (Box 2)
  - Review of Darwin's Biological work (Box 2)
  - Review of Evolution of Life (Box 2)
  - Review of Robert Nachtweg: Der Irrweg des Darwinismus (Box 2)
  - A visit to the USSR on behalf of the Scott Polar Research Institute, Roberts, Brian (Box 2)
  - Schmalhausen, I. I. (Box 2)
  - Science and the Scientist in the Soviet Union, Circa 1956; 20.0 p. (Box 2)
    Academic freedom; Genetics of plants; Kammerer, Paul; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich; Michurin, Ivan Vladimirovich; Political issues; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Science in Russia, n.d.; 3.0 p. (Box 2)
    History of biology, especially genetics -- U.S.S.R.; Lectures, public speaking; Russian politics and science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Scientific method in communist lands (Box 2)
  - Scientists and the visa problem (Box 2)
  - Soviet science and technology (Box 2)
  - Soviet scientific and technological capabilities (Box 2)
  - Status and trends in Soviet scientific and technical manpower resources (Box 2)
  - Stoletov, V. N. (Box 2)
  - Excerpt from "Just tell the truth.'', Strohm, John L (Box 2)
  - Unknown (Box 2)
  - Vasilenko, I. F. (Box 2)
  - Botanical-geographic principles of selection, 1935; 84.0 p.; Vavilov, N. I. (Box 2)
    Botany and plant genetics; Genetics of plants; Lenin All-Union Academy of Agricultural Sciences; Russian politics and science
  - Warecki, A. (Box 2)
  - Weterynaryjna, Med (Box 2)
  - Yudin, V. M. (Box 2)
  - Agrotechnical research on the sidewalk, Zhuravsky, V (Box 2)
- Botanical specimen books, 4 volumes
  - Ferns, part 1 (Volume 1)
  - Ferns, part 2 (Volume 2)
  - Algae, part 1 (Volume 3)
  - Algae, part 2 (Volume 4)